Guide to the Alliance for Guidance of Rural Youth records, 1887-1963 and undated, bulk 1914-1946 RL.10067
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Subject Files Series, 1919-1946 and undated, 7 boxes; 2.8 lin. ft.
  - Youth delinquency, 1929-1945, undated (Box 43)
  - Youth organizations - Misc., 1938-1945, undated (Box 43)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1919-1945 and undated, 3 boxes; 1.2 lin. ft.
  Contains notes and texts for speeches by Alliance members, chiefly Hatcher; copies of addresses presented by non-Alliance members at Alliance meetings; unpublished manuscripts and manuscript fragments; copies of scholarly articles published by Hatcher in educational, vocational, and women's journals; and radio broadcast scripts. Miscellaneous writings and speeches by Alliance members outline the history, purpose, and various activities of the Alliance. Miscellaneous writings and speeches by others contain information on more general subjects such as southern women, youth in industry, migrant war workers, postwar economic outlook and rural education. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Child Development and Guidance in Rural Schools (notes and ms. fragments), 1942 (Box 44)
  - Fifty Rural High School Girls (unpublished ms.), 1930 (Box 44)
  - Fifty Rural High School Girls (ms. fragments), circa 1930 (Box 44)
  - Findings of the 1944 Rural Guidance Institute (unpublished ms.), 1944, 2 folders (Box 44)
  - Guide to Wartime Washington, D. C. (youth migration handbook), 1944 (Box 45)
  - Hatcher, O. Latham speeches, 1919-1944, undated, 7 folders (Box 45)
  - Hatcher, O. Latham published articles, 1922-1946 (Box 45)
  - Memorials, 1932 (Box 45)
  - Misc. writings and speeches by Alliance, 1924-1943, undated(2 folders) (Box 46)
  - Misc. writings and speeches by others, 1928-1944, undated (Box 46)
  - Misc. writings and manuscripts fragments, n. d. (Box 46)
  - Occupations for Educated Women in Durham, Raleigh, and Winston-Salem, N.C. (unpublished ms.), 1926 (Box 46)
  - Radio broadcast scripts, 1925-1939, undated, 3 folders (Box 46)
  - When Our Young Folks Come Home to the Smaller Communities (unpublished ms.), circa 1945 (Box 46)
- Publications Series, circa 1918-1943, 2 boxes: 0.8 lin. ft.
  Arrangement note
  Materials published and distributed by the Alliance are divided into two groups. Smaller publications such as brochures, newsletters and conference proceedings are arranged alphabetically by type. Books and longer research reports are arranged chronologically by date of publication. Twenty-five Years of Work (1939) provides an extensive history of the organization. Miscellaneous file includes My Autobiography, a collection of forms used by the Alliance to gather data on rural youth, and A Syllabus for a General Course in Vocational Guidance. Also included are lists of publications.
  - List of publications, 1921-1939, undated (Box 47)
  - Annual reports, 1918-1919, 1921-1923, 1939-1941 (Box 47)
  - Brochures, circa 1919-1940 (Box 47)
  - Bulletins, 1921-1922, 1928-1929, 1932-1934, 1938, 3 folders (Box 47)
  - Conference proceedings, 1930-1943, 2 folders (Box 47)
  - Newsletters, 1924-1927, 1929-1936, 1943 (Box 47)
  - Misc., 1921-1939, undated (Box 48)
  - Occupations for Women, 1927 (Box 48)
  - Guidance Work in the Schools of Craven Counter, North Carolina, 1930 (Box 48)
  - Guiding Rural Boys and Girls, 1930 (Box 48)
  - A Mountain School, 1930 (Box 48)
  - Rural Girls in the City for Work, 1930 (Box 48)
  - Experimentation in Simple Guidance Programs for Rural Schools, 1931 (Box 48)
  - Handicaps of Elementary School Girls, 1931 (Box 48)
  - The Need for Guidance Programs in Privately Supported Mountain Schools, 1933 (Box 48)
  - Twenty-five Years of Work, 1939 (Box 48)
  - Child Development and Guidance in Rural Schools, 1943 (Box 48)
- Clippings and Press Releases Series, 1914-1946 and undated, 2 boxes; 0.6 lin. ft.
  Contains copies of articles published in newspapers and periodicals, book publishers' advertisements for Alliance publications, typescript copies of press releases concerning activities and publications of the Alliance, and lists of periodicals to whom the press releases were sent. Divided into two groups: general and book reviews. Each group arranged chronologically.
  - Alliance activities, 1914-1946, undated, 9 folders (Box 49)
  - Book reviews, 1923-1942, undated, 4 folders (Box 50)
- Photographic Materials Series, circa 1887-1930s, 3 boxes; 1.5 lin. ft.
  Black-and-white snapshots, nitrate negatives, and platinum prints depicting individuals living in rural areas of Kentucky, Virginia, North Carolina, and Tennessee. Most of the photographs and corresponding negatives were taken by Alliance staff in locations where vocational workshops or research projects were conducted: Breathitt County, Kentucky; Pine Mountain, Kentucky; Craven County, North Carolina; Ocracoke, North Carolina; Konnarock Training School, Virginia; Pleasant Hill Academy, Tennessee, and other mountain or rural mission schools. Included are two pictures of Rural Alliance leader Orie Hatcher and friends taken in 1887 and 1901.
  Also contains 41 original matted and signed 6x8 inch platinum prints, negatives, and other prints by photographer Doris Ulmann, taken in Kingdom Come and Hindman, Kentucky. These are for the most part carefully composed portraits of rural residents, commissioned by the Southern Women's Educational Alliance of Richmond. Subjects include family groups and individuals, chiefly children, youth, and women, but including some men; many individuals are identified by name in the Ulmann's notes, along with comments on their lives and personalities. One image shows a group of musicians with an African American fiddler, taken near Hindman, Ky. Another image taken by Ulmann in her studio features her assistant and Appalachian folklorist and musician John Jacob Niles. Includes a typed list of titles and notes for each print, identifying most individuals, and copies of photographs intended for publication, according to original folder titles.
  Series is arranged in two groupings: Alliance materials, and Doris Ulmann materials.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Nitrate negatives are closed to use; copies are available. Please contact the Rubenstein Library Research Services staff for assistance.
  - Alliance for Guidance of Rural Youth photographs, 1887-1930s
    - Photographs: Orie Latham Hatcher, 1887, 1901 (Box 51)
    - Photographs: Breathitt Co. Ky., circa 1920s-1930s (Box 51)
    - Photographs: Pine Mountain, Kentucky, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 51)
    - Photographs: unidentified, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 51)
    - Photographs: misc. and unidentified, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 51)
    - Photographs: manuscript fragments, circa 1930 (Box 51)
    - Photographs: manuscript fragments, circa 1930 (Box 51)
  - Negatives, 1920s-1930s? (NITRATE), 119 items 6 folders
    Scope and Contents
    Subseries contains nitrate film negatives from snapshots taken by Women's Education Alliance staff or others. The single sheet films measure roughly 2x2 or 2x3 inches. Images were taken by unidentified photographers chiefly in Kentucky, and Virginia, with some possibly in North Carolina. Place names that have been identified from original image and group titles are Breathitt (Ky.); Crozet (Va.); Red Hill (Scott County, Va.?); Konnarock Training School (KTS) and KHS, probably Konnarock High School (the largest group with a location), Whitetop (Va.); and Midway (Va.?).
    Subjects are chiefly girls and women, single individuals and groups. Hand-written notes photocopied by library staff from the wrappers that accompanied the negatives usually include first names and initials of last names, and occasionally there are details about family member relationships. Some buildings are visible, perhaps schools, and sometimes cars are in the picture.
    A few of the nitrate negatives are damaged or deteriorated but most are in good condition. They are closed to use but copies are available.
    - General (Box 52-A, Folder 1)
      Numbers RL.10067-N-0001 to N-0048
    - Midway [Virginia?] (Box 52-A, Folder 2)
      Numbers RL.10067-N-0049 to N-0057
    - Crozet [Virginia] (Box 52-A, Folder 3)
      Numbers RL.10067-N-0058 to N-0066
    - Red Hill [Virginia?] (Box 52-A, Folder 4)
      Numbers RL.10067-N-0067 to N-0086
    - "St. Pt." (Box 52-A, Folder 5)
      Numbers RL.10067-N-0087 to N-0095. Location has not been identified.
    - KHS [Konnarock High School, Virginia?] (Box 52-A, Folder 6)
      Numbers RL.10067-N-0096 to N-0119
  - Doris Ulmann photographic prints
    Contains a total of 42 signed, matted platinum prints by noted photographer Doris Ulmann that were commissioned by the Richmond branch of the Southern Woman's Educational Alliance and which were found among its archives. Titles and captions are taken directly from the inventory for 95 prints (represented by 92 entries); original spellings and colloquialisms have been retained. Although Ullman most likely authored the titles and captions, this has not been verified.
    The matted platinum prints are arranged in legacy identification number order (marked on backs), a system probably deriving from Rural Alliance staff who obtained the prints from Ullman for exhibition and publicity. They measure 6x8 inches, the size of the glass plate negatives used by Ullman, and are glued to original 11x14 inch cream-colored window mats with paper hinges, a few of which are detached. Most are signed by Ulmann in pencil on the mount, on the right side just below the print. The mats are fragile; please handle with care. The glass plates are not included in the collection; they may still exist within the New York Historical Society's large collection of Ullman photographs and negatives.
    - Oceola Phipps (Box 52, Folder 1, Image RL_10067_P_01)
      Age 14. Has made her own dresses since her ninth year. Wants to be a nurse. Is a very fine example of a blond mountain girl. Has great personal charm and with an equal chance would make her place anywhere in the world. Has had the usual education of a girl her age. Her parents favor her having a wider education.
      Legacy id number: 1A
    - Oceola Phipps (Box 52, Folder 1, Item RL_10067_P_02)
      Legacy id number: 1B
    - Oceola Phipps (Box 52, Folder 1, Item RL_10067_P_03)
      Legacy id number: 1C
    - Oceola Phipps (Box 52, Folder 1, Item RL_10067_P_04)
      Legacy id number: 1D
    - Mrs. Adams and her children (Box 52, Folder 1, Item RL_10067_P_05)
      Legacy id number: 24
    - Student at Methodist Settlement School at Kingdom Come (Box 52, Folder 2, Item RL_10067_P_06)
      She wants to be a doctor, and will, no doubt, succeed.
      Legacy id number: 28
    - Miss Whittaker (Box 52, Folder 2, Item RL_10067_P_07)
      Ran away from home because she did not like her stepfather. Come to Methodist Settlement School and is a model pupil. She is going to Washington to study Nursing.
      Legacy id number: 30
    - Miss Whittaker (Box 52, Folder 2, Item RL_10067_P_08)
      Legacy id number: 31
    - Little girl at Kingdom Come, with a clean dress and a little brother (Box 52, Folder 2, Item RL_10067_P_09)
      They were bright youngsters and good students.
      Legacy id number: 35
    - Ethel Holcolm, a rare singer and a very fine child (Box 52, Folder 2, Item RL_10067_P_10)
      She is a model student and a great blackberry picker.
      Legacy id number: 36
    - Ethel Holcolm and Tab Holcolm (Box 52, Folder 3, Item RL_10067_P_11)
      Legacy id number: 39
    - Gathel Holcolm (Box 52, Folder 3, Item RL_10067_P_12)
      Grandson of Mrs. Solomon Holcolm, of Kingdom Come.
      Legacy id number: 41
    - Mrs. Cornette, a rare singer and play actor, little Ethel Holcolm and John Jacob Niles (Box 52, Folder 3, Item RL_10067_P_13)
      Mr. Niles [noted folklorist and assistant to Ulmann] is recording the songs of both Mrs. Cornette and Ethel Holcolm. Mrs. Cornette left her blackberry preserving to come sing for the folks.
      Legacy id number: 42
    - Mrs. Cornette, a rare singer and play actor, little Ethel Holcolm and John Jacob Niles (Box 52, Folder 3, Item RL_10067_P_14)
      Legacy id number: 43
    - Headmaster of Kingdom Come School and a group of his friends and students (Box 52, Folder 3, Item RL_10067_P_15)
      Legacy id number: 45
    - Mr. Greer, carrying a burlap poke containing watermelon rinds for his hogs (Box 52, Folder 3, Item RL_10067_P_16)
      He is a republican and was born in Owsley County 85 years ago.
      Legacy id number: 47
    - Little children at the Fireside Industries School at Wooton, K.Y. (Box 52, Folder 3, Item RL_10067_P_17)
      Child on the left of Mary Munsey an extraordinary person and very pretty.
      Legacy id number: 54
    - Nola Josephs at the loom in the Fireside Industries at Wooton, K.Y. [3/4 frontal view] (Box 52, Folder 4, Item RL_10067_P_18)
      Legacy id number: 55
    - Nola Josephs at the loom in the Fireside Industries at Wooton, K.Y. (Box 52, Folder 4, Item RL_10067_P_19)
      Legacy id number: 56
    - Nola Josephs at the loom in the Fireside Industries at Wooton, K.Y. [back view] (Box 52, Folder 4, Item RL_10067_P_20)
      Legacy id number: 57
    - Children in creek at Wooton, K.Y. (Box 52, Folder 4, Item RL_10067_P_21)
      The oldest child was only 11, but managed the family perfectly. She spanked and delivered the law very successfully.
      Legacy id number: 60. Missing front of mat.
    - Children in creek at Wooton, K.Y. [Portrait of oldest girl seated] (Box 52, Folder 4, Item RL_10067_P_22)
      Legacy id number: 62
    - Children in creek at Wooton, K.Y. [Portrait of younger child, side view, with hand to eyes] (Box 52, Folder 4, Item RL_10067_P_23)
      Legacy id number: 63
    - Miss Grace Combs (Box 52, Folder 4, Item RL_10067_P_24)
      Has had a little learnin at the Richmond, K.Y., Normal School, and has taught a little. She is truly a beauty of the most extraordinary type. She has, however, great naivete and could almost be called bashful. She wants to see the outside world.
      Legacy id number: 67
    - Miss Grace Combs (Box 52, Folder 4, Item RL_10067_P_25)
      Legacy id number: 68
    - Miss Grace Combs (Box 52, Folder 4, Item RL_10067_P_26)
      Legacy id number: 69
    - Miss Grace Combs (Box 52, Folder 5, Item RL_10067_P_27)
      Legacy id number: 70
    - Dale Smith, daughter of Senator Smith (Box 52, Folder 5, Item RL_10067_P_28)
      Legacy id number: 71
    - Dale Smith and Miss Combs (Box 52, Folder 5, Item RL_10067_P_29)
      Legacy id number: 72
    - Kindergarten teacher at Hindman School [Ky.] (Box 52, Folder 5, Item RL_10067_P_30)
      Legacy id number: 73
    - Courtday in Courthouse at Hindman, K.Y. [Front of courthouse from distance with about 40 individuals on steps and balcony, almost all men] (Box 52, Folder 5, Item RL_10067_P_31)
      Legacy id number: 74
    - Old lady with the sunflower dress (Box 52, Folder 5, Item RL_10067_P_32)
      She came visiting on Sunday and sang lovely songs, too.
      Legacy id number: 78
    - Judge Begley and his wife (Box 52, Folder 5, Item RL_10067_P_33)
      The Judge is highly thought of in those parts, that is, Hyden, K.Y.
      Legacy id number: 79
    - Begley children, taken a Sunday at Hyden, K.Y. [Portrait of young girl standing by chair] (Box 52, Folder 5, Item RL_10067_P_34)
      Legacy id number: 80
    - Begley children, taken a Sunday at Hyden, K.Y. [Portrait of young girl with a bow in her hair, seated on ground] (Box 52, Folder 5, Item RL_10067_P_35)
      Legacy id number: 81
    - Begley children, taken a Sunday at Hyden, K.Y. [Portrait of young girl seated in chair] (Box 52, Folder 5, Item RL_10067_P_36)
      Legacy id number: 84
  - Ulmann prints "for publication"
    Four photographic prints, matted and numbered as the others, but separately housed with title "for publication." Arranged in legacy id order. The portrait of Mr. Greer and the Fireside Industries children are closely related to other prints in the collection.
    - Ethel Holcomb and Tab Holcolm (Box 52, Folder 7, Item RL_10067_P_37)
      Legacy id number: 40
    - Mr. Greer, carrying a burlap poke containing watermelon rinds for his hogs [Close-up] (Box 52, Folder 7, Item RL_10067_P_38)
      Legacy id number: 46
    - Little children at the Fireside Industries School at Wooton, K.Y. (Box 52, Folder 7, Item RL_10067_P_39)
      Legacy id number: 53
    - Fred Stampler's group of fiddlers [Portrait of two male musicians - a white guitarist and a black fiddler - a "Mr. Storr" - and two seated women, near Hindman, Ky.] (Box 52, Folder 7, Item RL_10067_P_40)
      Legacy id number: 65
      This may be a mis-titled print, as there is only one fiddler. The guitarist has not been positively identified as Fred Stampler. There was a large family of musicians in Hindman by the name of Stamper (Hiram). The fiddler is unidentified in this image, but a solo portrait of the same individual shows up in other Ulmann collections as "Mr. Storr".
  - Other prints, 2 items
    - John Jacob Niles playing lap dulcimer, [1930?], 6 x 8 in. (Box 52, Folder 8, Image RL_10067_P_41)
      Portrait of Niles (1892-1980), noted folklorist, musician, and field assistant to Ulmann, reportedly taken in her N.Y. studio in 1930. He is shown seated and playing a lap dulcimer. Black-and-white unmatted print; possibly an oil pigment process. No legacy id number was identified.
    - Scenic view of mountain range, [1937?], 6 x 8 in. (Box 52, Folder 8, Image RL_10067_P_42)
      Glued to thin board with inscription in lower left corner of print: Staley [9?]37. May have been taken by Staley Brothers Studio in Tullahoma, Coffee County, Tennessee. Both brothers reportedly were taking photographs into their 70s; brother William Staley died in 1937.
  - Paper copies of Ulmann prints
    Four printed paper copies of Ulmann portrait photographs of rural children; the images measure 6x8 inches, with the overall sheet dimensions measuring 11x14. One is a duplicate image already in the collection (#41); the other three are the only images in the collection. Only one has a title and a legacy id.
    - Gathel Holcolm (Box 52, Item RL_10067_PR_01)
    - [Young girl holding another young girl, with flowers bunched in each hand] (Box 52, Item RL_10067_PR_02)
      No original legacy id number or title was found. This does not seem to be represented in the list of 95 prints found in the collection.
    - [Blond girl leans out of window] (Box 52, Item RL_10067_PR_03)
      No original legacy id number or title was found. This does not seem to be among the list of 95 prints found in the collection.
    - [Boy looks out of window, chin in hands] (Box 52, Item RL_10067_PR_04)
  - Doris Ulmann copy prints and inventory of prints with notes, 25 items
    - Copy prints, undated (Box 52-A)
      Twenty-five unmatted black-and-white 8x10 inch glossy prints of a selection of Doris Ulmann prints, produced at an unknown date. A few are duplicate images.
    - Inventory of 95 prints, undated (Box 52-A)
      Set of typed notes on thin paper giving the number identification, title, and caption details for 95 prints (all of which were most likely commissioned by the Richmond branch of the Alliance for the Guidance of Rural Youth), 42 of which are in the collection. The titles and texts are by the photographer, Doris Ulmann. A photocopied set is available for use. There are also several sheets of loosely written penciled notes in an unidentified hand on topics related to the Alliance's plans for the images.
- Oversize Materials, 1920-1942 and undated., 1 box
  Arrangement reflects order of series in main collection.
  - Administrative Files Series. Heaven Bound (playbill), 1934 (Box 53)
  - Administrative Files Series. President's annual report, 1920, 1925 (Box 53)
  - Administrative Files Series. Rural youth study: Youth migration in Virginia counties (proposal), 1935-1939, undated (Box 53)
  - Administrative Files Series. Vocational survey in southern colleges, circa 1919-1926 (Box 53)
  - Breathitt Co. Project Files Series. Survey (data compilations, circa 1935, 3 folders (Box 53)
  - Subject Files Series. Negro occupations [original title], 1928-1942, undated (Box 53)
  - Publications Series. Brochures (SWEA membership poster), undated (Box 53)
  - Publications Series. Newsletters, 1925-1926 (Box 53)